Ekaterina Lobacheva

Home page / Google Scholar / GitHub

e-mail: lobacheva.tjulja@gmail.com tel: +79166498371

I'm a deep learning researcher at Bayesian Methods Research Group supervised by Prof. Dmitry Vetrov. My research interests now mainly focus on understanding the properties of neural networks training and loss landscape. I am also interested in scaling laws for neural network models, ensembling methods and their connection to the shape of networks loss landscape, analysis of object representations obtained in different training paradigms, and in general self-supervised and transfer learning. The results of my work were published at NeurIPS, AAAI, EMNLP, ICCV.

*denotes joint firs	t co-authorship
Training Scale-Invariant Neural Networks on the Sphere Can Happen in Three Regimes, NeurIPS 2022 Maxim Kodryan*, Ekaterina Lobacheva*, Maksim Nakhodnov*, Dmitry Vetrov	arXiv / code
On the Periodic Behavior of Neural Network Training with Batch Normalization and Weight Decay, NeurIPS 2021 Ekaterina Lobacheva*, Maxim Kodryan*, Nadezhda Chirkova, Andrey Malinin, Dmitry Vetrov	arXiv / code
On Power Laws in Deep Ensembles, NeurIPS 2020 (Spotlight) Ekaterina Lobacheva, Nadezhda Chirkova, Maxim Kodryan, Dmitry Vetrov	arXiv / code
Structured Sparsification of Gated Recurrent Neural Networks, AAAI 2020 (Oral) Ekaterina Lobacheva*, Nadezhda Chirkova*, Alexander Markovich, Dmitry Vetrov	arXiv / code
Bayesian Compression for Natural Language Processing, EMNLP 2018 Nadezhda Chirkova*, Ekaterina Lobacheva*, Dmitry Vetrov	arXiv / code
Deep Part-Based Generative Shape Model with Latent Variables , BMVC 2016 Alexander Kirillov, Mikhail Gavrikov, Ekaterina Lobacheva , Anton Osokin, Dmitry Vetrov	paper
Joint Optimization of Segmentation and Color Clustering, ICCV 2015 Ekaterina Lobacheva, Olga Veksler, Yuri Boykov	paper
WORKSHOP PUBLICATIONS / PREPRINTS	
To Stay or Not to Stay in the Pre-train Basin: Insights on Ensembling in Transfer Learning, 2023 Ildus Sadrtdinov*, Dmitrii Pozdeev*, Dmitry Vetrov, Ekaterina Lobacheva	3 arXiv
On the Memorization Properties of Contrastive Learning, ICML 2021 OPPO Workshop Ildus Sadrtdinov, Nadezhda Chirkova, Ekaterina Lobacheva	arXiv
Deep Ensembles on a Fixed Memory Budget: One Wide Network or Several Thinner Ones?, 2020 Nadezhda Chirkova, Ekaterina Lobacheva, Dmitry Vetrov	arXiv
Adaptive prediction time for sequence classification, 2018 Maksim Ryabinin, Ekaterina Lobacheva	paper
Monotonic models for real-time dynamic malware detection, ICLR Workshop 2018 Alexander Chistyakov, Ekaterina Lobacheva, Alexander Shevelev, Alexey Romanenko	arXiv
Semantic embeddings for program behavior, ICLR Workshop 2017	arXiv

Alexander Chistyakov, Ekaterina Lobacheva, Arsenii Kuznetsov, Alexey Romanenko

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

2020 - 2022 Research Fellow and Deputy Head, Centre of Deep Learning and Bayesian Methods, HSE University

I worked mostly on understanding the properties of neural networks training and loss landscape. Specifically, my work was focused on sharp and flat optima, mode connectivity, ensembling methods and specifics of training of networks with normalization layers. I also worked on the scaling laws for deep ensembles. The results were published at NeurIPS.

2018 - 2020 Research Fellow, Samsung-HSE Laboratory at HSE University

I worked on Bayesian sparsification methods for recurrent neural networks, including embedding layers and gated layers such as LSTM. The results were published at EMNLP and AAAI.

2015 - 2018 Junior Researcher, Kaspersky Lab

I worked on feature extraction techniques and classification models for dynamic malware detection. The results were published at ICLR Workshops and were built into company antivirus products.

Summer Research Intern, University of Western Ontario

2014 I worked on the improvement of energy-based segmentation methods for the case of camouflage

images. The results were published at ICCV. Advisors: Yuri Boykov and Olga Veksler

EDUCATION

2022 PhD in Computer Science, HSE University

Thesis on: Deep learning architectures on a fixed memory budget Advisor: Dmitry Vetrov

Cum Laude

2009 - 2014 Specialist degree (BSc+MSc) in Computer Science, Lomonosov Moscow State University

Thesis on: Boltzmann machines for image segmentation Advisor: Dmitry Vetrov

Graduated with honors (GPA 5.0 out of 5.0)

TECHNICAL SKILLS

- I mostly program in **Python** but also have some experience with C++
- I am fluent with common data science tools such as NumPy, matplotlib, scikit-learn, pandas
- My primary deep learning framework is **PyTorch** (prior to that, I had experience with Theano+Lasagne and TensorFlow)
- I'm comfortable with the common data science environment e.g., bash, git, Linux, GPU clusters

THESIS SUPERVISION AND CO-SUPERVISION

- Ildus Sadrtdinov (finishing his MSc at HSE University)
 - On the Memorization Properties of Contrastive Learning (BSc, 2021)
 - Ensembling Neural Networks in the Transfer Learning Setup (MSc, 2023)
- Sergey Troshin (now a PhD student at University of Amsterdam)
 - Deep Equilibrium ResNet (BSc, 2020)
- Maksim Ryabinin (now finishing his PhD at HSE University and works in Yandex Research)
 - Gradient Optimization of Beam Search Hyperparameters (BSc, 2019)
- Polina Kirichenko (now a PhD student at NYU)
 - Study of Bayesian Regularization of Neural Networks (BSc, 2018)
- Nadezhda Chirkova (now Research Scientist at Naver Labs)
 - Bayesian Compression for Natural Language Processing, (MSc, 2018)

TEACHING

2016 - Now	Research seminar Machine Learning and Applications, Faculty of Computer Science at HSE University
2015 - 2021	Bayesian Methods in Machine Learning (organization + seminars) , HSE University, MSU, and Yandex School of Data Analysis
2018 - 2019	Neurobayesian models (organization + seminars), HSE University, MSU, and Yandex School of Data Analysis
2017	Introduction to Deep Learning (Online course at Coursera, lectures)
2016 - 2017	Deep learning (lectures and seminars), MSU
2016 - 2017	Machine learning (lectures), HSE and HSE/NES Programmes in Economics
2015 - 2017	Data analysis (seminars), HSE University

Additionally, I was one of the main organizers of Deep|Bayes Summer School at 2017-2019 and gave several lectures and seminars there. Also, we with Nadezhda Chirkova gave a tutorial on Bayesian machine learning at Machine Learning in High Energy Physics Summer School (Hamburg, Germany, July 2019 and online, July 2020 and 2021) and Workshop on Machine Learning and Applications to Physics (Madrid, Spain, Dec 2019).

PROGRAM COMMITTEE

Neural Information Processing Systems, NeurIPS (reviewer, 2019–2021):

- 2019: top-50% highest-scored reviewers
- 2021: outstanding reviewer award (top-8%)